Finding Aid for Amaranth Club (Jackson, Mich.) records, 1898-1992
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Amaranth Club (Jackson, Mich.) records 1898-1992 1920-1980
Amaranth Club (Jackson, Mich.)
2 linear feet.
90166 Bk 2
Catholic women's literary club of Jackson, Michigan. Historical materials, minutes of meetings, meeting programs, and scrapbooks detailing club activities.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were received from Mrs. Paul Crigo (donor no. 7799 ) in May 1990.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Amaranth Club of Jackson, Michigan was established in October 1897 and was the second women's Catholic literary club in Michigan; the first was the Catholic Woman's Study Club of Detroit. The Amaranth Club was the first Catholic Literary Club to join the State Federation of Clubs in 1904.
The Amaranth Club was founded by Mrs. James Falihee who thought that there should be a Catholic literary club in Jackson in addition to the other literary clubs that already existed. The first year, 1897-98, the Amaranth Club numbered 23 members. At its founding the object of the Amaranth Club was "mutual improvement," and this object has been in the bylaws to the present. The women of the club presented their own programs, book reviews, readings, plays, debates, skits and musical presentations often having to do with current events and topics. The Amaranth Club met weekly from October through April.
The Amaranth Club was primarily a literary club, not a charity club. However, throughout the years it donated much of its time and effort to charitable causes, especially during the depression and war years. A Student Loan Fund was established in the late 1920s.
The records of the Amaranth Club date from 1898 to 1990, with the bulk dating from 1920 to 1980, and measure 2 linear feet. The collection has been broken down into four series: Historical Materials, Meeting Minutes (1921-1979), Meeting Programs (1898-1980), and Scrapbooks.
Subjects:
Amaranth Club (Jackson, Mich.); Catholic Church--Michigan--Jackson--Societies, etc.; Jackson (Mich.); Literature--Societies, etc.--Michigan--Jackson.; Women--Michigan--Jackson--Societies and clubs.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Historical Materials
  The Historical Materials are comprised of several histories of the Amaranth Club written by members at different points of the history of the club.
  - Various histories, various dates (Box 1)
- Meeting Minutes, 1921-1979
  The Meeting Minutes (1921-1979) make up about half of the collection. Until 1965 they were written out longhand in bound volumes; after 1965 they were typed on loose paper. Financial reports are included until 1965 in the bound volumes, but not after. There are also newspaper clippings and other miscellaneous items in the bound meeting minutes. The minutes give a detailed account of each meeting, describing not only the topic of the meeting but also sometimes what people wore and ate. The minutes are complete except for the years 1897-1920, 1937-1939, and 1955-1959. At the end of this series is a list of members from 1966-1980 that was found at the end of the loose, unbound minutes.
  - December 13, 1921-November 20, 1923 (Box 1)
  - October 7, 1924-April 26, 1927 (Box 1)
  - October 4, 1927-April 1, 1930 (Box 1)
  - April 8, 1930-February 21, 1933 (Box 1)
  - February 28, 1933-March 24, 1936 (Box 1)
  - October 1, 1940-March 21, 1944 (Box 1)
  - October 3, 1944-March 25, 1947 (Box 1)
  - October 5, 1947-February 27, 1951 (Box 1)
  - March 6, 1951-February 8, 1955 (Box 1)
  - October 27, 1959-March 23, 1965 (Box 1)
  - September 25, 1965-December 9, 1969 (Box 1)
  - January 13, 1970-March 26, 1974 (Box 1)
  - October 15, 1974-December 13, 1977 (Box 1)
  - January 10, 1978-December 11, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Amaranth Club members (1966-1980) (Box 1)
- Meeting Programs, 1899-1992
  Meeting Programs were printed for each year and list the topics of each program. A member list and a copy of the bylaws are printed at the end of each program. The series is almost complete from 1898 to 1980. Only the following years are missing: 1941-42, 1942-43, 1943-44, 1970-71, and 1977-78.
  - 1899/1900-1909/1910 (Box 2)
  - 1910/1911-1919/1920 (Box 2)
  - 1920/1921-1929/1930 (Box 2)
  - 1930/1931-1939/1940 (Box 2)
  - 1940/1941-1949/1950 (Box 2)
  - 1950/1951-1959/1960 (Box 2)
  - 1960/1961-1969/1970 (Box 2)
  - 1970/1971-1979/1980 (Box 2)
  - 1991/1992 (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks
  The Scrapbook series is comprised of two scrapbooks; both have been unbound as they are very fragile. The first scrapbook contains newspaper clippings and other items relating to the Amaranth Club and its members. The first part of the second scrapbook is a collection of clippings and other memorabilia of the Athena Club, another women's literary club in Jackson, Michigan which was established in 1885. The second half is made up of clippings of the Amaranth Club. Perhaps a member of the Amaranth Club had previously belonged to the Athena Club and simply continued her scrapbook when she switched clubs.
  - Miscellaneous Loose Items (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Amaranth Club, 1922-1952 (scattered dates) (Box 2)
  - Athena Club and Amaranth Club, 1927-1966 (scattered dates) (Box 2)